Guide to the Philip M. and Lorna Sarrel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Philip M. and Lorna Sarrel papers
1966-2007
1966-1980
MS 1922
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
33
(90 boxes)
The papers comprise biographical information of Philip M. and Lorna Sarrel; files documenting the establishment of the Young Mothers Program (YMP) at Yale-New Haven Hospital, an outgrowth of the teenage pregnancy clinic; the inclusion of sex education courses in curricula for a New Haven high school and Yale undergraduate and medical students; audiotapes of Sarrel's lectures; films, mostly commercially produced, depicting aspects of human sexuality for the training of college students and medical personnel; and related writings by Sarrel and others.
Sarrel, Philip M., 1937-
Sarrel, Lorna J.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip M. and Lorna Sarrel, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Copies of commercially produced audiovisual materials contained in this collection cannot be made for researcher use outside of the repository.
Separated Materials
Macy Conference on Family Planning, Demography & Human Sexuality in Medical Education, Williamsburg, Va., 1970, was removed from the Sarrel papers and added to Manuscripts and Archives publications.
Biographical / Historical
Philip M. Sarrel received his bachelor's degree from Dartmouth College and his medical degree from New York University School of Medicine in 1963. He completed his internship at Mount Sinai Hospital and his residency in Obstetrics and Gynecology at the Yale-New Haven Medical Center where he became the director of the teenage pregnancy clinic in 1964, later known as the Young Mothers Program. Following his appointment to the faculty in 1969, the year that co-education was instituted at Yale, Sarrel and his wife Lorna, a psychiatric social worker holding degrees from Mount Holyoke College and Columbia University, both trained by Masters and Johnson in sex therapy, founded the Yale Sex Counseling Service. They also instituted the first Yale class dealing with human sexuality and produced a student booklet, "Sex at Yale." In 1984, Dr. Sarrel was appointed director of the Mid-Life Study Program. He has remained at Yale throughout his career, earning the rank of Full Professor in 1988 and is currently Emeritus Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Psychiatry at Yale University School of Medicine. Sarrel is the author and co-author of over 200 medical articles and chapters for medical texts and the co-author of six textbooks related to menopause and to understanding sexual behavior and response.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise biographical information of Philip M. and Lorna Sarrel; files documenting the establishment of the Young Mothers Program (YMP) at Yale-New Haven Hospital, an outgrowth of the teenage pregnancy clinic; the inclusion of sex education courses in curricula for a New Haven high school and Yale undergraduate and medical students; audiotapes of Sarrel's lectures; films, mostly commercially produced, depicting aspects of human sexuality for the training of college students and medical personnel; and related writings by Sarrel and others.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by topic and alphabetically or chronologically therein.
Sex; Sex counseling; Sex educators; Sex instruction; Teenage mothers; Teenage pregnancy; Sex customs; LGBTQ resource; Sarrel, Lorna J.; Sarrel, Philip M., 1937-; Yale-New Haven Hospital; Yale New-Haven Hospital. Young Mothers Program; Yale University -- Students -- Sexual behavior; Yale University. School of Medicine; Yale University. Student Committee on Human Sexuality
- Interview, 2007 July 24; 3 computer files (WAV)
  Scope and Contents
  The interview was conducted by Kelly Morrow at the Sarrel's home.
  - Use copies, 3 compact discs (CD-R) (Box 1.1Ua–1.1Uc)
  - Transcript, 2007 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Young Mothers Program (YMP) at Yale-New Haven Hospital
  A multi-disciplinary program established in 1965 to provide medical and community services to unmarried pregnant teenagers in the New Haven area.
  - "The Young Unwed Primipara: A Study of 100 Cases with Five Year Follow-Up", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Pilot Demonstration in Reaching Out to Teen-age Unwed Parent", [1966] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Resident's Role in an Unwed Mothers Program", [1966] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Study of Programs for Unwed Teenage Mothers", 1967 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Analysis of deliveries between September 1965 and December 1966 to girls in the YMP, 1967 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re funding, 1967 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "European Programs for the Care of the Unwed Mother and Her Child," research material, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "A Total Community Approach", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Role of the Psychiatrist in the Young Mother's Program, July 1967 to December 1967" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Young Unwed Mother-Obstetrical Results of a Program of Comprehensive Care", 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "First Quarterly Research Report (Covering September, October, and November 1967)", 1968 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Twelve Month Report to Clinical Staff of Young Mothers Program", 1968 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Supplementary progress report, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings authored and co-authored by Philip Sarrel relating to teenage pregnancy, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Writings of others relating to teenage pregnancy, 1967, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Yale School of Medicine
  - "Chief Resident's Report", 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Joint report by Drs. Sarrel and DiSaia.
  - Report on the establishment of sex education courses for medical students and related professions, Circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Recent Trends and Developments in Medical Education in Family Planning and Human Sexuality-A Survey Report," by Philip M. Sarrel, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Human sexuality course offered to medical students and related materials, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes list of lectures and students' written objectives for taking the class.
- Sex education programs
  - Correspondence, 1966 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Richard C. Lee High School, Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Report documents the establishment of sex education classes at the high school level and the role of Philip Sarrel as consultant.
  - Yale University and "Topics in Human Sexuality"
    A series of lectures, films, and group discussions offered to Yale students and the Yale community, led by Philip Sarrel and others. Sponsored by the Yale Student Committee on Human Sexuality.
    - Sex Knowledge and Attitude Questionnaires, 1973-1989, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
      Anonymous questionnaire filled out by participants upon admission to course.
    - Yale Student Committee on Human Sexuality announcements, 1983-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper clippings regarding the Sarrels and sex education at Yale, 1968-1988, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publications by the Sarrels and others regarding sex education and college students (expand folder), 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Sex counseling
  Not necessarily specific to New Haven or Yale programs.
  - "Communication and Sexology-Working with a Major TV Network," draft, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes critiques of shows by the Sarrels as consultants in standards and practices for the American Broadcasting Company (ABC).
  - "The Dual Therapy Approach to the Treatment of Sexual Dysfunction", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Paper presented by the Sarrels at the World Health Organization (WHO) Conference, Geneva.
  - "Sexual Unfolding in Adolescents," draft, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Audiotapes of lectures, including course in Human Sexuality
  Arranged chronologically. Descriptions taken from containers.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - "Understanding Sexuality: Psychologically, Socially and From a Development Point of View," by Dr. Coplin, 1970 February 2; 4 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 3–6)
  - "Sex Response," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1970 February 16
    - Lecture 1, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 7)
    - Lecture 2, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Lecture 3, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
  - "Pregnancy and Birth," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1970 February 23; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 10–12)
  - "Contraception," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1970 March 2; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 13–15)
  - "Abortion," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1970 March 9; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 16–18)
  - "Focus on Scene at Yale," by Dr. and Mrs. Sarrel, 1970 April; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel)
    - Lecture 1, 1 (Box 19)
    - Lecture 2, 1 (Box 20)
    - Lecture 3, 1 (Box 21)
  - "Interpersonal Relationships," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, Law School Auditorium, 1971; 3 (Box 22–24)
  - "Anatomy and Physiology," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, Law School Auditorium, 1971; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 25–27)
  - "Contraception," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, Law School Auditorium, 1971; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 28–30)
  - "Abortion," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, Yale Law School Auditorium, 1971; 3 aduiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 31–33)
  - "Pregnancy and Birth," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, Yale Law School Auditorium, 1971; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-rel) (Box 34–36)
  - "Sex and the College Student: Psychological Aspects and Concerns," by guest lecturer, Dr. Lorraine Siggins, Yale Law School Auditorium, 1971; 2 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 37–38)
  - "Sex is a Natural Function," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 February 7; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 39–41)
  - "Sex Values and Interpersonal Relationships," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 February 14; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 42–44)
  - "Understanding Sexual Function and Dysfunction," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 February 21; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel)
    - Lecture 1 (Box 45)
      General
      1 audiotape (reel-to-reel)
    - Lecture 2, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 46)
    - Lecture 3, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 47)
  - "Contraception," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 February; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 48–50)
  - "Abortion, Sterilization, V.D., and How to Manage Your Mother's Menopause, et al," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 March; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 51–53)
  - "Pregnancy and Birth," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 March 13; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 54–56)
  - "Introduction and Male Sexuality," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 fall; 2 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 57–58)
  - "Female Sexuality, by Mrs. Lorna Sarrel, 1972 fall; 1 audiotape (Reel-to-reel) (Box 59)
  - "Female Homosexuality," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 fall; audiotape (Reel-to-reel) (Box 60)
  - "Male Homosexuality," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 fall; audiotape (Reel-to-reel) (Box 61)
  - "Contraception," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 fall; audiotape (Reel-to-reel) (Box 62)
  - "Various Questions and Answers on Human Sexuality," by Dr. Philip Sarrel, 1972 fall; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 63)
  - "Female Sexuality, by Lorna Sarrel, 1980 January 21; audiotape (Reel-to-reel) (Box 64)
  - "Lecture 1," Sarrel, 1972 October 30; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 65–67)
  - "'Human Sexuality, Lecture 1, parts 1-3," by Sarrel, Undated; 3 audiotapes (Reel-to-reel) (Box 68–70)
- Films
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Descriptions taken from containers.
  - The Bed, Palmer Film Services, Grove Press, Inc., Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16 mm), color, 20 minutes, 700 ft. (Box 71)
  - The Erogenists, Circa 1971; Commercially produced film reel (16mm) approximately 425 ft. (Box 72)
    Possibly by L. Sutton, Multi Media Resource Center, California.
  - Female Masturbation #132, Focus International, Inc., Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm) (Box 73)
  - First Date, filmmakers Mariko Tse and Sam Joseph, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), 5 minutes (Box 74)
  - Free, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm) (Box 75)
  - Give to Get, filmmaker Laird Sutton, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), color, 11 minutes, approximately 400 ft. (Box 76)
  - Holding, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm) (Box 77)
  - Home Movie, J. Oxenberg, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), color (Box 78)
  - Looking for Me, #7782, edited version, University of California, Extension Media Center, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), 20 minutes (Box 79)
  - Male Masturbation, Focus International, Inc., Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16 mm), approximately 200 ft. (Box 80)
  - Norien Ten, filmmaker John Knoop, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), color, 10 minutes. (Box 81)
  - Physiological Responses of The Sexually Stimulated Female in the Laboratory, Yale University Center for Media Initiatives, 2004 August 18; Commercially produced film reel (16mm) (Box 82)
  - A Quickie, filmmaker Dirk Kortz, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (8mm) (Box 83)
  - Rich and Judy, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16 mm) (Box 84)
  - Sex at Yale, Sarrel produced film, 1970-1971; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), approximately 400 ft. (Box 85)
  - Squeeze Technique, filmmaker Laird Sutton, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel ( 16mm), color, 12 minutes. (Box 86)
  - Touching, filmmaker Laird Sutton, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), black and white, 17 minutes, approximately 600 ft. (Box 87)
    Beginning of film missing.
  - Unfolding, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), approximately 700 ft. (Box 88)
  - Vir Amat, directed by Laird Sutton, [1971]; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), approximately 650 ft. (Box 89)
  - Words of Love (Talk is Cheap), filmmaker Dirk Kortz, Multi Media Resource Center, California, Undated; Commercially produced film reel (16mm), 5 minutes. (Box 90)
    Sound track off.